# Curriculum Vitae Dr. Fabrice Lacroix

"I am a biogeochemical scientist passionate in understanding the role of biogeochemistry and ecosystems in a changing environment. My research has focused on coupling hydrological and biogeochemistry dynamics in terrestrial, riverine and oceanic systems, with the coastal ocean as a vital connector. I aim to contribute to constantly evolving observational-based datasets and apply them to constrain cutting-edge modeling frameworks."

Citizenships Canada, Switzerland, France

ORCID <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4749-2826">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4749-2826</a>

Google Scholar ID <a href="https://scholar.google.de/citations?user=8mIU">https://scholar.google.de/citations?user=8mIU</a> wQAAAAJ&hl=de

# **Education and Degrees**

**07.2019 Ph.D. in Science** 

Université Libre de Bruxelles, Brussels, Belgium

Max-Planck-Institute for Meteorology, Hamburg, Germany

Dissertation title: "Global and regional contributions of riverine fluxes to

the global and regional oceanic cycling of carbon and nutrients"

Advisors: Prof. Dr. Pierre Regnier, Prof Dr. Tatiana Ilyina

07.2015 M.Sc. in Environmental Science

ETH Zürich, Zürich, Switzerland

Thesis title: Offshore transport of carbon in the California current system

10.2013 B.Sc. in Environmental Science

ETH Zürich, Zürich, Switzerland

## **Current Positions**

03.2024 - Ambizione Fellow, Senior Scientist, Junior Group Lead

Institute of Geography & Oeschger Centre for Climate Change Research, University of Bern, Switzerland

# **Past Academic Positions**

04.2022-01.2024	Postdoctoral Researcher
	Climate and Environmental Physics & Oeschger Centre for Climate Change Research, University of Bern, Switzerland
09.2023-11.2023	Guest Researcher (2.5 months), UniBe Travel Grant Recipient
	Laboratory of Climate Extremes, Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina, Brazil
04.2020- 04.2022	Research Associate, Postdoctoral Researcher
	Department Biogeochemical Signals, Max-Planck-Institute for Biogeochemistry, Jena, Germany
07.2019 - 03.2020	Postdoctoral Researcher
	Department Ocean in the Earth System, Max-Planck-Institute for Meteorology, Hamburg, Germany
09.2015 - 07.2019	EU H2020 Marie Skłodowska-Curie Early-Stage Researcher
	Université Libre de Bruxelles, Brussels, Belgium / Max-Planck-Institute for Meteorology, Hamburg, Germany

# Other Employment

03.2015-06.2015	Intern Climate Accounting
	Climate-KIC, Zürich, Switzerland
11.2014-02.2015	Intern Casualty Risk Engineering
	XL Insurance (Acquired by Catlin Insurance), Zürich Switzerland

# **Teaching and Lectures**

09.2024 –	Co-Lecturer for "Land in the Earth System II" - M.Sc. Climate Science Graduate course
	University of Bern, Bern, Switzerland
09.2022 - 01.2024	<b>Tutorial and Lab Course Assistant</b> for the lectures "Physics for Medical Undergraduates" and "Physics for Biology and Pharmacy Undergraduates"
	University of Bern, Bern, Switzerland
01.2021	<b>Lecturer</b> of Ph.D. introductory course "Atmosphere, Ocean & Land 2021" - Ph.D. Level Course
	Max Planck Institute for Biogeochemistry, Jena, Germany

**O9.2019** Tutorial Assistant at Max Planck Institute Earth System Modelling

Summer School 2019 - Ph.D. Level Course

Max-Planck-Institute for Meteorology, Hamburg, Germany

**O9.2011 - 08.2014** Tutorial Assistant for Introductory Chemistry 1 & 2 – Undergraduate

Course

ETH Zürich, Switzerland

**02.2012 - 01.2014 Tutorial Assistant** for Systems Analysis

ETH Zürich, Switzerland

## **Supervision**

**O7.2024- Supervisor** to Lara Oxley, Ph.D. Candidate at *University of Bern, Bern* 

Switzerland

**08.2023** - Advisor to Yu Zhu, Ph.D. Candidate at *Max Planck Institute for* 

Biogeochemistry, Jena, Germany

## **Funding, Proposals and Awards**

2023	Awarded Ambizione Fellowship, 2022 Call (covering 799'000 CHF /
	889'076 USD), covering own salary and a that of a PhD candidate for 4
	years, with the project "Past and Future Perturbation of the Pan-Arctic
	Nitrogen Cycle" to be pursued at University of Bern, Switzerland

2023 Awarded Travel Grant by University of Bern (covering 2'800 CHF / 3116

USD) for projects "Cascading Impacts of Climate Change in the South Atlantic" to be pursued at Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina,

Florianopolis, Brazil

2022 Contributor to accepted Swiss National Computing Centre computing time

proposals OVERSHOOT (large proposal) and AERA (small proposal)

2020-2021 Contributor to annual project report Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft

project CASPER

2020 Contributor to successful computing time request proposal EU Horizon

2020 project CRESCENDO

2019 Contributor to Annual Report Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft project

**PALMOD** 

2017 Outstanding Student Poster, 10th International Carbon Dioxide Conference,

Interlaken, Switzerland

2015-2019 Contributor to annual and final project reports for EU Horizon 2020 Marie

Sklodowska-Curie innovative training network C-CASCADES

# **Selected Conference and Workshop Presentations**

**Lacroix** et al.:. Persistent High-Latitude Ocean Warming and Global Sea Level Rise Following Temporary Overshoots. *EGU General Assembly 2024*, Vienna (**Oral**)

**Lacroix** et al.: Enhanced Transports from Land-to-Ocean: Towards Boundless Assessments of Carbon and Nitrogen Cycles. *Oeschger Centre for Climate Change Seminar*, University of Bern, 6 Dec 2023. (**Invited, Oral**)

**Lacroix** et al.: Riverine Influence on the global ocean CO<sub>2</sub> flux. *R2O-MIP Workshop*, <u>SOCAT pCO2</u> Workshop Series, Nov 2023, Ooostende, Belgium. (Invited Oral)

**Lacroix** et al. Towards a boundless Earth system: Do riverine and coastal disruptions affect marine greenhouse gases and ecosystems at the global scale? Oct 2023, *Seminar Oceanografia*, University of Sao Paulo, Brazil. (**Invited Oral**)

**Lacroix** et al.: Temporal Disconnect of Seasonal Plant Nutrient Demand and Thaw Depth implies an Increasing Source of N<sub>2</sub>O in High-Latitude Permafrost Ecosystems. *EGU General Assembly 2022*, Vienna, Austria (**Oral**)

**Lacroix F.**, Ilyina, T., Mathis, M., Laruelle, G., Regnier, P.: Past century increases of terrestrial nutrient inputs impact both the coastal and open ocean carbon cycle. *EGU General Assembly 2021*, Vienna, Austria (**Oral**)

Regnier, P. & Lacroix, F.: Coastal Ocean CO<sub>2</sub> fluxes and C cycle. *Ocean Carbon Budget Workshop* Jun. 2021, Online Workshop (Invited, Oral)

**Lacroix, F.** & Regnier, P: F<sub>nat</sub>, more than just river-induced carbon outgassing? *Global Carbon Budget Ocean Workshop*, "Carbon Gaps", Feb. 2021, Online Workshop (**Invited, Oral**)

**Lacroix F.** Ilyina, T., Mathis, M., Laruelle, G., Regnier, P: Short coastal water residence times support an efficient cross-shelf transfer of organic matter: Were pre-industrial continental shelves already a global CO<sub>2</sub> sink? *Ocean Sciences* Meeting 2020 (**Oral**)

## **Selected Workshops**

2019	C-CASCADES ITN Training Workshop – Entrepreneurial skills: Deltares, Delft, Netherlands.
2017	C-CASCADES ITN Training Workshop – Diagenic models and Earth system models of intermediate complexity. <i>University of Exeter, Cornwall, United Kingdom.</i>
2014	Avenues in the Tropics, <i>Barranquilla, Colombia</i> . Sustainable urban planning lab and workshop co-organized by Universidad del Norte (Colombia), ETH Zürich (Switzerland) and the World Bank (USA).

## **Publication List**

#### In Review

Schuster, L., et al. (incl. **Lacroix, F.**): Irreversible glacier change and trough water for centuries after overshooting 1.5° C. In review for *Nature Climate Change*.

Silvy, Y. et. al. (incl. **Lacroix, F.**): AERA-MIP: Emission pathways, remaining budgets and carbon cycle dynamics compatible with 1.5 °C and 2 °C global warming stabilization, EGUsphere [preprint], https://doi.org/10.5194/egusphere-2024-488, 2024.

### **Published / in Press**

#### 2024

**Lacroix, F.**, Burger, F., Silvy, Y., Frölicher, T.L. (2024): Persistent Sea Level Rise and High Latitude Warming Following Overshoot Scenarios. In press for *Earth's Future*.

Schleussner et al. (Lacroix, F.), Overconfidence in climate overshoot. In press for Nature.

Liu, M. et al. (Incl. **Lacroix, F.**): Revised river C flux to the global ocean based on model and observations. *Nature Geoscience*, 2024

Yolandi, E. et al. (Incl. **Lacroix, F.**): "The African regional greenhouse gases budget (2010–2019)." *Global Biogeochemical Cycles* 38.4 (2024): e2023GB008016.

Mathis, M., **Lacroix, F.**, Hagemann S., Nielsen, D., Ilyina, T., Schrum, C. (2024): Enhanced CO<sub>2</sub> uptake of the coastal ocean is dominated by biological carbon fixation. *Nature Climate Change*. https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs-2928105/v1

Resplandy, L. et al. (incl. **Lacroix, F.** 2024). A synthesis of global coastal ocean greenhouse gas fluxes. *Global Biogeochemical Cycles*, 38, e2023GB007803. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2023GB007803">https://doi.org/10.1029/2023GB007803</a>

#### 2023

**Lacroix F**. Arctic Rivers tell Tales of Change. *Nature Geoscience*, 16, 760-761. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-023-01248-6

Schaller, J. et al. (incl. **Lacroix, F.**, 2023): Arctic soil CO2 release during freeze-thaw cycles modulated by silicon and calcium. *Science of the Total Environment*, 870, 161943. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2023.161943

Stimmler, P. et al. (incl. **Lacroix, F.,** 2023): Pan-Arctic soil element availability estimations. *Earth System Science Data*, 15, 1059–1075. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-15-1059-2023">https://doi.org/10.5194/essd-15-1059-2023</a>

### 2022

Mathis, M., Logemann, K., Maerz, J., **Lacroix, F**., Hagemann, S., Chegini, F., et al. (2022). Seamless integration of the coastal ocean in global marine carbon cycle modeling. *Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems*, 14, e2021MS002789. https://doi.org/10.1029/2021MS002789

**Lacroix, F.**, Zaehle, S., Caldararu, S., Schaller, J., Stimmler, P., Holl, D., Kutzbach, L., & Göckede, M. (2022). Mismatch of N release from the permafrost and vegetative uptake opens pathways of increasing nitrous oxide emissions in the high Arctic. Global Change Biology, 28, 5973–5990. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.16345">https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.16345</a>

Dai, M., Su, J., Zhao, Y., Hofmann, E.E., Cao, Z., Cai, W.-J., Gan, J., **Lacroix**, F., Laruelle, G.G., Meng, F., Müller, J. D., Regnier, P.A.G., Wang, G., Wang, Z (2022): Carbon Fluxes in the Coastal Ocean: Synthesis, Boundary Processes and Future Trend, *Annual Review of Earth and Planetary Sciences* 50(1). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-earth-032320-090746">https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-earth-032320-090746</a>

### 2021

**Lacroix, F.**, Ilyina, T., Mathis, M., Laruelle, G. G., & Regnier, P. (2021): Historical increases in land-derived nutrient inputs may alleviate effects of a changing physical climate on the oceanic carbon cycle. *Global Change Biology*, 00, 1–23. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.15822">https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.15822</a>

**Lacroix, F.**, Ilyina, T., Laruelle, G. G., & Regnier, P. (2021): Reconstructing the preindustrial coastal carbon cycle through a global ocean circulation model: Was the global continental shelf already both autotrophic and a CO<sub>2</sub> sink?. *Global Biogeochemical Cycles*, 35, e2020GB006603. https://doi.org/10.1029/2020GB006603

### 2020

**Lacroix F.**, Ilyina T. & Hartmann, J. (2020): Oceanic CO<sub>2</sub> outgassing and biological production hotspots induced by pre-industrial river loads of nutrients and carbon in a global modeling approach, *Biogeosciences*, 17, 55–88. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-17-55-2020">https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-17-55-2020</a>

## **Datasets**

**Lacroix, F.**, Liu, M., Ma, M., Resplandy, L., Beusen, A., Hauck, J., Lennartz, S., Li, Y., Tian, H., & Regnier, P. (2024). Biogeochemical river inputs for global ocean models (RivR2O) [Data set]. Zenodo. https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13799103

Lacroix, F., Burger, F., Silvy, Y., Schleussner, C.-F., & Frölicher, T. L. (2024). GFDL-ESM2M overshoot data [Data set]. Zenodo. https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.11091132

Lacroix, F., Zaehle, S., Caldararu, S., Schaller, J., Stimmler, P., Holl, D., Kutzbach, L. & Göckede, M. (2022). Coupled C-N-P QUINCY terrestrial biosphere enhanced for high latitude simulations over 1960-2018 for the high-Arctic region. Global Change Biology. https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.6832235